[Music]
lichen planus is a chronic autoimmune
disease typically of our moist membranes
such as the inside of our mouth but can
also affect other body surfaces
and it's not that rare around one
percent and making it to one of the
commoner conditions seen in oral
medicine clinics
current treatments are not curative but
rather palliative aimed at relieving
pain we've tried steroids antibiotics
chemotherapy surgery and not appear to
be particularly effective
so even for palliative pain relief we
don't have great options so that's why
case reports like this are so exciting
here's the before
and here's the after one month then two
three six seven months later
after
drinking two ounces of aloe vera juice a
day and applying aloe topically as well
with these kinds of before
and after cases leading to journal
articles with titles like aloe vera as a
cure for lichen plainness
but is ingested oral aloe vera
potion or poison
internal use of aloe may cause acute
hepatitis liver inflammation as well as
electrolyte imbalances and
you should definitely not inject aloe
but oral use is also not recommended
either
this is primarily because of case
reports of aloe-induced hepatitis aloe
was ironically presented as a
detoxifying product but can actually end
up causing liver damage like in this guy
he was trying to protect his liver and
ended up in the hospital
how do we know it was the aloe though
the assessment of suspected herbal
induced liver injury is challenging
because there's hundreds of things out
there that can damage your liver
here's the kind of checklist you have to
go through as a doctor
to rule out other causes before you
blame it on the plant do you have some
kind of viral hepatitis or other kind of
liver infection or could be various
drugs or toxins or diseases so maybe
it was one of these other things it was
just a coincidence that the problem
started after drinking aloe
the gold standard in terms of trying to
prove cause and effect is a positive
re-exposure test
that's how you diagnose drug induced
liver injury liver inflammation
disappears when you remove the drug and
then reappears when you add the drug
back
which is rarely done for obvious reasons
well has there ever been a re-challenge
case published for aloe
yes
aloe induced toxic hepatitis that shot
up again after stopping and then
restarting aloe ingestion
aloe consumption has also been linked to
thyroid dysfunction a woman with lichen
planus started swallowing two teaspoons
of aloe vera juice a day she started
feeling unjustifiably tired
lab work showed her thyroid function was
low but she perked right back up after
stopping the aloe and her thyroid
function returned to normal
what if instead of swallowing though she
just swished the aloe around her mouth
to try to help the like and plainness
and then spit it out
we didn't know until it was
put to the test
a randomized double-blind
placebo-controlled trial 54 patients
randomized to a topical aloe vera gel or
placebo gel for eight weeks
eighty-one percent in the aloe group got
better compared to just four percent in
the placebo group
furthermore two patients treated with
aloe had a complete
clinical remission that's that's rare i
mean it's considered a chronic condition
yet a few weeks applying aloe these
nasty erosive lesions
disappeared
how about compared to a steroid ointment
though
topical aloe vera gel was
superior
more effective than the steroids a
significant difference appearing within
two weeks
so although corticosteroids are still
considered the gold standard aloe vera
shows promising results especially with
no adverse effects when applied
topically compared to various adverse
side effects of the corticosteroids
that's for oral like in planus though
what about the efficacy of aloe vera gel
in the treatment of lichen planus of the
genitals like implants of the vulva is
quite common affecting one to two
percent of the population
and it may be even harder to treat
there are flares and partial remission
but no tendency for complete remission
and indeed that's what they saw in the
placebo group
one woman had a good response but most
had little or no response but applying
aloe vera gel instead
and 9 out of ten responded and one woman
had a complete clinical remission
they conclude that aloe vera gel is a
safe
and effective treatment
[Music]
foreign